<section xml:id="essential_clarifications_section"  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>
  Commentary
</title>

<introduction>
  For the purposes of MAS 170, the contents of this section should be considered as
  amendments to Freedman, <em>Statistics</em> <xref ref="freedman_statistics"/>.
</introduction>

<subsection>
  <title>Rounding in calculations
</title>

<p>In general, do not round off any numbers in a multi-step calculation
until the final step. If you must round, keep lots of digits. A rule of
thumb is to round to the nearest <m>0.001</m>, that is, to the nearest
3rd digit to the right of the decimal point.
</p>

<p>Exceptions: When calculating a <m>z</m>
  value for normal data, you may round to the nearest 0.01, because
  that's the level of accuracy in the <m>z</m>
  column on the normal table. When calculating an area under the normal
curve, you may usually round the final answer to the nearest whole
percent.
</p>
 
</subsection>


<subsection>
  <title>Percentile (pp.90<ndash/>91)</title>

  <p>The <term>percentile rank</term>
    of a data value <m>A</m>
    is the percent of all data whose value is less than or equal to
    <m>A</m>. If the percent of data less than or equal to <m>A</m>
    is <m>p</m>, then <m>A</m>
    has <m>p</m>-th percentile. In picture form, the percentile rank of
    a data value <m>A</m>
    is the area under the histogram to the left of <m>A</m>. The text
    introduces percentile and percentile rank in the context of normally
    distributed data, but the terms percentile and percentile rank apply
    to all types of data, whether it is normally distributed or not.
</p>
</subsection>


<subsection>
  <title>
    The term <q>football-shaped</q>(p.120)</title>

  <p>The text uses the term <q>football-shaped</q>
    or <q>shaped like a football</q>
    very loosely throughout Ch 8<ndash/>12 to describe a scatter diagram
    that has linear association. Worse, the term <q>football-shaped</q>
     is
sometimes used to imply homoscedasticity. Even worse, "football-shaped"
is used to imply that data in thin vertical strips in the scatter
diagram is normally distributed (see the box on p.197). Because of this
vagueness and ambiguity, we will instead use the terms "shows linear
association", "homoscedastic", and "data in thin vertical strips is
normally distributed" for these various attributes that may or may not
apply to 2-variable data. In particular, in the box on p.197, and also
in item 7 of the Ch 11 summary on p.201, replace the first sentence with
"Suppose that a scatter diagram shows linear association, is
homoscedastic, and data in thin vertical strips is normally
distributed."</p>
</subsection>



</section>


