  <section>
    <title>Definition of a <em>geometry</em>
    </title>	       

    <introduction>

      <p><em>Geometry</em> is the study of shape and properties of
	configurations of points. 
	A central concept is that
	of <em>congruence</em>. In his 1872 work called
	the <em>Erlangen Programm</em>, Felix Klein unified various
	notions of geometry using transormation groups of
	congruences. Here is a version of Klein's definition.

<definition xref="geometrydefn"><title>Geometry</title><statement><idx>geometry</idx>
    A <term>geometry model</term><idx><h>geometry</h><h>geometry
	model</h>
    </idx>
    is a pair <m>(G,X)</m>, where <m>G</m> is a group acting
    on a set <m>X</m>, called the <term>(model) space</term>. Subsets of <m>X</m> are
    called <term>figures</term>. Figures <m>F,F'</m> are
    called <term>congruent</term> if there is a transformation <m>g</m>
    in <m>G</m> such that <m>g(F)=F'</m>.
</statement></definition>
		
	To introduce what this means, we begin
      with a comparison of properties of line segments and angles in a flat
	plane versus lines segments and angles on the surface of a
      sphere. For now, we appeal to the intuition and avoid technical
	definitions.
      </p>

      <p>
	A (straight) "line segment" can be defined, both for the plane and
	the sphere, as a path of shortest possible length that
	connects two points. On the sphere, these length minmimizing
	paths are arcs of great circles (that is, circles made by
	intersecting the sphere with planes that pass through the center
	of the sphere). In addition to distance and straight lines,
	angles between straight line segments make sense both in the
	plane and on the sphere. Here a some notable differences between
	the plane and the sphere that illustrate the phrase "properties
	of configurations of points".

      <ul><li>A (straight) "railroad track" is a pair of straight line
      segments that are a constant distance apart. It is possible to
      map out railroad tracks in the plane, but not on the sphere,
      where it is impossible to have a pair of straight line segments
	  that are a constant distance apart.</li>
	<li>In the plane, the sum of the three interior angles of any
	  triangle is 180 degrees, or <m>\pi</m> radians. On the sphere,
	  the sum of the interior angles of a triangle
	  is <em>greater</em> than 180 degrees, and can be as great as
	  540 degrees.
	</li>
      </ul>
      These differences in properties of parallel lines and angle sums in
      triangles are expressions of the differences in shape possessed by the
      flat plane and the sphere. In order to define "shape" and
      "geometry" more precisely, we blah blah blah

      In order to proceed from these observations do not point
      to an obvious definition of shape.
      </p>
    </introduction>
    
    <subsection>

      <p>We begin with a story that introduces the modern concept of
	a <em>geometry</em>. Imagine an ant civilization in which
	surveyor ants have the ability to measure distances with tiny
	ant measuring sticks and to measure angles with tiny ant
	protractors. Ants call a path
	between two points "straight" if that path has the shortest
	length of all possible paths that start at one of the points and
	end at the other. Now imagine that two of these surveyor ants
	go out in the world to make maps for
	possible train tracks (that is, two parallel straight lines at a
	fixed distance apart). Surveyor ant <m>A</m> ends up on a
	large flat surface, say, a perfectly smooth and flat table, and
	surveyor ant <m>B</m> ends up on a large spherical surface, also perfectly
	smooth. 
      </p>

      <p>The two surveyors come back with the following reports. (put in a figure here)
	<ul><li><em>Ant <m>A</m>, from table world
	</em>: I was able to map many possible railroad tracks. I checked many triangles, and I find that the
	    three interior angles of all of those triangles sum to a
	    total of one-half revolution.<fn>That's 180 degrees,
	      or <m>\pi</m> radians. Ants are not troubled by awkward human
	    rotation measure conventions.
	    </fn>
	  </li>
<li><em>Ant <m>B</m>, from sphere world
	</em>: I was not able to map out a single railroad track: for
	every pair of straight paths I checked, those paths either
	became further apart or closer together. I found a triangle whose
	three interior angles sum to a total of one and one-half
  revolutions. </li>
	</ul>
	From their experiences with small flat surfaces (like flat
	rocks) and small round surfaces (like round fruit), the ants
	were able to hypothesize that the differences in their empirical
	evidence was due to differing <em>shape</em> of the worlds they
	were measuring.
      </p>

      <p>
The point of this parable is that the situation for the ants is not so
different for humans. We also live in a big world with limited tools and
experience.  Driven by practical concerns of engineering and navigation,
the subject of geometry began with experiments and empirical data to
achieve better understanding.  The term "geometry" comes from the Greek
roots meaning "measurement of the earth".

</p>

      
    </subsection>

  <subsection>
    <p>
      Two geometries are equivalent if there are the right kind of
      equivariant maps between them. Example: 
      Möbius geometry as projective geometry of the projective space
      of <m>\C^2</m>, introduce stereographic projection as a tool.

    </p>

  </subsection>
</section>
