<chapter xml:id="relations_section"  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
<title>
Relations
</title>


<section><title>Basic objects</title>

  <p>
The following definitions clarify and expand the definitions given in
<xref ref="chapterzero"/>.
  </p>

    <p>The following is an amendment to Definition 4.1.4 on p.66 of
      <xref ref="chapterzero"/>.
</p>

  <p>
    <definition>
      <p>Let <m>A,B</m> be sets. A <term>relation from <m>A</m>
      to <m>B</m></term> is a subset <m>R\subseteq A\times B</m> of the
      Cartesian product <m>A\times B</m>. A relation from a set <m>A</m>
      to itself is called a <term>relation on the set <m>A</m></term>.
      Given a relation <m>R</m>
      from <m>A</m> to <m>B</m>, the <term>inverse relation</term>
      to <m>R</m>, denoted <m>R^{-1}</m>, is the relation
      from <m>B</m> to <m>A</m> given by
      <me>R^{-1} = \{(b,a)\colon (a,b)\in \R\}.
      </me></p>
    </definition>
  </p>

      <p>The following is a clarification of the term <em>directed
      graph</em> introduced in Example 4.1.7 on
	p.67 of <xref ref="chapterzero"/>.
      </p>

    
  <p>Given a relation <m>R</m> on a set <m>A</m>, a <term>directed
      graph</term> is a figure that illustrates <m>R</m>. Elements
    of <m>A</m> are depicted as dots, and <m>(a,a')</m> in <m>R</m> is
    depicted by a segment of a line or an arc that starts at <m>a</m>,
    ends at <m>a'</m>, and has an arrow pointing from <m>a</m>
      to <m>a'</m>. 
  </p>

  <p>The following is a <alert>correction</alert>
    to Definition
      4.4.1 on p.84 of <xref ref="chapterzero"/>.
	</p>
	
  <p>
    <definition>
      <p>A <term>(simple) graph</term> is a pair <m>G=(V,E)</m>,
      where <m>V</m> is a set and <m>E</m> is a set of subsets
      of <m>V</m>, where every element of <m>E</m> has two elements. An
      element of <m>V</m> is called a <term>vertex</term> and an element
      of <m>E</m> is called an <term>edge</term>. The
      set <m>V</m> is called the <term>set of vertices</term> of the
      graph <m>G</m>, and the set <m>E</m> is called the <term>set of
	  edges</term> of <m>G</m>. </p>
    </definition>

    One can also define graphs that allow loops, that is, edges that
    connect a vertex to itself. Further generalizations of graphs allow
    multiple edges that connect the same pair of vertices. In this
    course, the term <q>graph</q> will always refer to a simple graph,
    as defined above. <fn>The
      definition of graph given in <xref ref="chapterzero"/> uses the
      word <q>pair</q> in the definition of an edge. Unfortunately, this
    introduces ambiguity as to whether loops are allowed as edges. In mathematics, the
      word <q>pair</q> usually denotes an <em>ordered</em>
      list <m>(x,y)</m>. By default, it is allowable that the
      objects <m>x</m> and <m>y</m> may be equal. We avoid this ambiguity
      by not using the word <q>pair</q> in our definition of graph.
    </fn>

  </p>

</section>


</chapter>
